Hello, for this task we have some algebraic
datatypes, namely 'Animal' and 'Bit' with
their constructors 'Cat', 'Dog', 'Bird', and 'O'
and 'I' for 'Bit'; for simplicity, however, I'm
going to refer to them as 0 and 1 here because
we're talking about bits, and it's easier to say.
Our actual task here is to write an encode
and a decode function that can take lists of
our type 'Animal' and convert them to a list of
type 'Bit', and the decode function should be the
reverse of this. So a list of type 'Bit' should
result in a 'Maybe' list of type 'Animal', 'Maybe'
because one of the requirements is that for every
list of type 'Bit' for which no corresponding
original list of type 'Animal' exists, the function
decode should return the value 'Nothing', so if we
somehow get a messed-up list of bits here which
we can't decode into a proper list of animals,
we should just return nothing and be done with
it. And the other requirement is for every list
of type 'Bit' that can be produced by encode, the
function decode should return the value 'Just L';
So this is the other side of our Maybe where we
have a valid list of animals, and this L is exactly
the original as before applying encode, so that
basically means these functions shouldn't just
run independently of each other but need to use
the same encoding strategy in the background
which is obviously something we need to come up
with. We are not going to start with our encode
function immediately though because this works
on a list of animals, to make it a little easier
for us we're gonna make a helper function that
just encodes a single animal into a list of bits;
It's gonna be a list of bits because obviously
we have only two bits but three animals, so we
can't just do a simple one-to-one encoding, so
some of the animals are going to be encoded into
multiple bits, and the easiest way to do that
is just to create a list of bits for that; so
we're going to do this with simple pattern
matching here because we only have three
constructors for animals, so it's not going to be
that big of a deal, and if we just write these out we
have our encode 'Animal' for 'Cat', 'Dog', and
'Bird', and now we need to come up with the actual
encoding for each of these. Like I already
said, some of these are going to have to be
multiple bits; let's just start with
the first one just walking through it...
and now we have our 'Cat' and 'Dog',
and for the 'Bird', we now need to, as
our task already tells us down here, find
some kind of space-efficient encoding, so not
using an unnecessarily long list of bits, so
two bits is the longest we should have here,
because obviously if we needed to go past
two, we need to have more than four animals,
but we only have three animals here, so we don't
even need to use two bits for every single one of
these; for 'Bird' we can just pick one bit, let's
just do O here, and then thinking about how we're
gonna be decoding this in the end, it's gonna make
it a little easier if we're doing it like this,
obviously we can't do a single I as well
because then we would need to be checking if
this is actually the end of this encoding or if
something's following; this can get confusing
and actually might be impossible
to implement like this.
Because for 'Cat' and 'Dog' we wouldn't know if
we're just looking at a 1 bit; is this now a
'Cat' or a 'Dog' or is this just a single
bit, a 'Cat' or 'Dog' where a second bit
follows the encoding, or is this just a
just a single 'Bird'? So we need to keep a
O bit here, so now the encoding is more clear.
If we are going to be decoding this in the
end we have a list of bits stringed
along with no separation like this,
so if the first bit we're looking at is a 1, it
could be either 'Cat' or 'Dog', so if it's a 1 bit
we just need to look at the bit following
afterwards; if it's another 1 it's a 'Cat',
if it's an O it's a 'Dog', and if what we're looking
at is just an O then it's definitely a 'Bird'.
That's our 'encodeAnimal' function, and we obviously
need to apply that to the entire list of animals.
Which is actually pretty easy because if you look
at our structure here we have a single 'Animal'
being encoded to a list, and we want
to end up with a flat list, so if we
apply this with a map function, for example, we
can apply our 'encodeAnimal' like this with map,
so if you think about the interaction here how
this is going to be used, encode is going to
wait for another parameter which is the
list that map applies 'encodeAnimal' to,
and in this case, map would just apply encode
animal to every animal, and we would end up with
a list of bit lists inside of it, so we need
to flatten this down so we can compact this...
and then that's our encode function. Obviously
we can simplify this one step further,
because there's a ready-made 'concatMap'
function in the Prelude, because this is a
pretty common operation, and that's our encode
taken care of. So this would encode any list of
type 'Animal' into a list of type 'Bit', and now
we need to look at the decode function to do the
reverse of this, and obviously catch all the cases
where it's an invalid list of bits, which has no
corresponding list of animals for it. So we just
start with this most simple case, for an input
of type list, obviously this is the empty list,
and is an empty list a valid 'Animal' list? If
you think about it, yeah, because for a list of type
'Animal', the empty list is always part of the set,
so for this we can return just an empty list
because an empty list of type Bit is just an
empty list of type Animal as well. The second
case is going to be our first case where it's
an invalid list, as we can see in our encoding
up here we have these two; we're not going to
be matching for these, but for the case where it's
just a single element, there's one case where it's
an invalid list, which is if it's a list with just
one bit that doesn't decode into an 'Animal', and
no 'Animal' is encoded into just a single
'I' bit, so this is going to be our case of
an invalid input list of bits, so we return
'Nothing'. And now we need to start actually
looking through the list recursively because for
every input list which starts with a valid 'Bit'
encoding afterwards there could be more animals
obviously, so if we just start with the next
most simple case, it would be a list that starts
with a 0 bit and then follows up with anything
and for that, for example, we could do guards here
and check, first of all, recursively basically
if our remaining part after the zero is actually
valid because we know the zero can only be a
'Bird', so we need to look at the remaining part;
can this be a valid list? And so we can check
'isNothing' to catch this 'Nothing' case
that might come up in our rest of the list,
which we need to decode recursively here,
and if this is the case, if it's 'Nothing',
'isNothing' returns a Boolean; if this value here
is 'Nothing', then it's 'Nothing', which ends True.
So, in that case, we return 'Nothing', because
we found one invalid part somewhere in this step,
which makes the entire list invalid, and then our
otherwise case would be if the rest of the list
is fine; there's no 'Nothing' found in there, so
we can return 'Just Bird' and then recursively
get the other animals from the list, which,
since the rest of this is also going to be
'Maybe's, we need to
get our 'Just Animal' out of there, so we're
going to do 'Just' and then decode the rest again.
And at this point, you may have noticed that
we are using 'decode xs', which is going to
be a pretty expensive operation, since this is
recursively walking through the rest of the list.
We're doing this twice, which we shouldn't do if
we can avoid it, so we're going to do a where
clause here, which contains our 'decode xs', which
we're just going to name 'rest', and then we're
going to insert that into these places, and that's
already much simplified, because we don't do two
unnecessary recursions in here; we are only
walking through the list recursively once.
And for our next case, which would obviously
be the list starting with the I bit...
This time, we need to look at the first bit;
we're matching for our first bit—that's I,
and we need to look at the second bit because our
'Cat's and 'Dog's encoding are always two bits,
and the rest of the list, of course,
once again, we're gonna do this with
guards; here we're checking for
'isNothing' on the rest of this again,
I'm gonna do the where clause for this
in a moment, and the otherwise case is
'Just'... and now we need to do the separation
between 'Cat' and 'Dog'; if our second bit is
a 1 bit, then it's a 'Cat', and the only
other 'Bit' would be a 0 bit, so we don't need
to specifically check for that; so it's just the
else case, and it's a 'Dog', and once again the
rest of our list, which is 'fromJust rest' again,
so we have our where clause with 'decode xs'.
And that's our decoding, but we can
improve on this a little further because...
We're using 'fromJust' here,
which is basically extracting
the value inside of 'Just something'. We can avoid
using this altogether, and we can avoid using the
where clause as well if we just change this over
to a case expression, so we're going to keep
this pattern-match on the list starting with the 0
bit, but we're going to change all of this over to
'case decode xs', so we're basically changing
our where clause to be up here—'decode xs of'...
If our 'decode xs' returns 'Nothing', then it's
an invalid list, and we should keep returning
'Nothing', and if it's 'Just rest', so this is
our case with 'Just', and that's the value in our
'Just' we can immediately name this here, so
we don't need to extract it with 'fromJust'.
Then we are returning 'Just Bird',
because this case for 0 bit to start
and rest; we don't need to use 'fromJust'
again here because we basically extracted
it with our case expression, and we do the
same treatment for our other decode case.
'decode xs' again, and once again if it's
'Nothing', so some kind of invalid list,
keep returning 'Nothing' and 'Just rest',
extracting the rest of the list again,
then we return 'Just', and once again we'll
check for the second bit to determine if
it's a 'Cat' or a 'Dog' and the rest, and that's
our decode function. Okay, now if we save this...
load it into ghci...
and run the tests, you can see the
tests pass, and that's our test solved.